Guide to the Raul Salinas Papers, ca. 1950-1994
Department of Special Collections
Raul Salinas Papers,
ca. 1950-1994
Special Collections M0774
Salinas, Raul
ca. 20 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Purchased from Raul Salinas, 1995.
BIOGRAPHY
Raul / Roy / "Tapon" Salinas was born in San Antonio, Texas on March 17, 1934. He was raised in Austin, Texas from 1936 to 1956, when he moved to Los Angeles. In 1957 he was sentenced to prison in Soledad State Prison in California. Over the span of the next 15 years, Salinas spent eleven years behind the walls of state and federal penitentiaries. It was during his incarceration in some of the nation's most brutal prison systems that Salinas' social and political consciousness was shaped. His prison years were prolific ones, including creative, political, and legal writings, as well as an abundance of correspondence. In 1963, while in Huntsville, he began writing a jazz column called "The Quarter Note" which ran for eighteen months. In Leavenworth he played a key role in founding and producing two important prison journals, Aztlan de Leavenworth and New Era Prison Magazine. It was in these journals that his poetry first circulated and gained recognition within and outside of the prison walls. As a spokesperson, ideologue, educator, and jailhouse lawyer of the prisoner-rights movement, Salinas also became an internationalist who saw the necessity of making alliances with others. This vision continues to inform his political and poetic practice. Initially published in the inaugural issue of Aztlan de Leavenworth, "Trip thru a Mind Jail" (1970) became the title piece for a book of poetry published by Editorial Pocho Che in 1980. With the assistance of several professors and students at the University of Washington -Seattle, Salinas obtained early release from Marion Federal Penitentiary in 1972. As a student at the University of Washington, Salinas worked in various community development projects and forged alliances with Native American groups in the Northwest, a relationship that was to intensify over the next fifteen years. Although Salinas writes of his experiences as a participant in the Native American Movement, it is a dimension of his life that has received scant attention. In the twenty-two years since his release from Marion, Salinas' involvement with various political movements has earned him an international reputation as an eloquent spokesman for justice. Salinas literary reputation in Austin has earned him recognition as the poet laureate of the East Side and the title of "maestro" from emerging poets who seek his advice and leadership. His literary work is perhaps most widely known for its street aesthetics and a sensibility which documents the interactions, hardships, and strife of barrio and prison life. The influence of jazz within his oeuvre connects it with the work of "Beat Generation" poets, musicians, and songwriters. His poetry collections include dedications, references, and responses to Allen Ginsberg, Jack Kerouac, Charles Bukowski, Charles Parker, Herschel Evans, Dizzy Gillespie and Miles Davis, for example. This guide was written by Emmet Campos, Dana Maya Maynard, Louis Mendoza at the University of Texas at Austin in spring 1994. The Raul Salinas Collection was processed in spring 1998 by Scott Boehnen and Erika Beer of the Department of Special Collections, Stanford University.
CHRONOLOGICAL BIOGRAPHY
1934 -1936 San Antonio, Texas.
1936 -1956 Austin, Texas.
1956 -1957 Los Angeles, California.
1957 -1959 Soledad State Prison, California.
1959 -1961 Austin, Texas.
1961 -1965 Texas State Prison, Huntsville, Texas.
1963 -1965 Publishes prose; poetry; and "The Quarter Notes," a monthly jazz column for The ECHO (Huntsville, TX).
1965 -1967 Austin, Texas.
1967 -1971 U.S. Federal Penitentiary, Leavenworth, Kansas.
1969 -1971 Assistant editor of New Era Prison Magazine, Leavenworth Penitentiary
1969 Cofounder of Chicanos Organizados de Rebeldes de Aztlan, study group at Leavenworth Federal Penitentiary, Kansas.
1970 -1971 Editor and writer for Aztlan de Leavenworth (prison journal publication).
1971 -1972 U.S. Federal Penitentiary, Marion, Illinois.
1971 -1972 Member of Federal Prisoners International Coalition, Federal Penitentiary, Marion, Illinois
1972 Drafting committee member for "Brainwashing Techniques in Prison" (report on prison abuses). Marion, IL.
1972 -1976 Member of Centro de la Raza; Assistant Director, Jose Marti Day Care Center; cofounder of Resistencia Bookstore in the Centro, Seattle, Washington
1972 -1977 Seattle, Washington.
1973 publishes Viaje/Trip (chapbook) Providence: Brown University.
1973 Counselor for Office of Minority Affairs, University of Washington, Seattle
1974 Edits Vortice (journal). Stanford: Stanford UP.
1974 Reads for Festival Flor y Canto I, U.S.C.
1974 Reads for Festival Sexto Sol, Stanford University.
1974 Reads for Festival Santa Clara.
1974 -1976 Member of the American Indian Movement Northwest Chapter; presenter for Indian/Chicano Education, Seattle, Washington.
1975 -1977 Media Spokesperson and Trail Coordinator for Survival of American Indians, Frank's Landing, Washington.
1977 -1978 San Francisco, California.
1975 Participates in Venceremos Brigade to Cuba.
1976 Coordinates Cross-country Educational Caravan, Trail of Self Determination, Washington State to Washington D.C.
1977 Participates in Venceremos Brigade to Cuba
1977 -1980 Cofounder of the Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, Seattle, Washington; Rapid City, South Dakota; and Milwaukee, Wisconsin.
1978 -1979 Lecturer, Spanish and Portuguese, Chicano Studies, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington.
1978 -1980 Seattle, Washington
1979 Spokesman for Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, Puerto Rico.
1980 Spokesman for Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, Canada.
1980 Publishes Un Trip Through the Mind Jail y Otras Excursions. San Francisco: Editorial Pocho Che, 1980.
1980 -1985 Austin, Texas.
1980-1986 Leonard Peltier Support Group (founder), Austin, Texas
May 1980 Representative for Leonard Peltier at Canto Al Pueblo: A Four Arrows Symposium, Mesa, Arizona.
July 1980 Participates in Annual Youth and Elders Conference, Philip Deere's Camp, Okemah, Oklahoma.
May 1981 Leads four-person delegation to Yellow Thunder Camp, South Dakota.
June 1981 Leads four-person Austin delegation to Annual Memorial, Oglala, South Dakota.
1981 Spokesperson for Leonard Peltier Defense Committee at the NGO Conference on Indigenous Philosophy and the Land in Geneva, Switzerland.
1981 Delegate and translator, International Indian Treaty Council, Nicaragua (for U.N. Seminar on Racial Discrimination).
1981 Board Member of El Centro Chicano, Austin, Texas.
1981-1984 League of United Chicano Artists (LUChA), Board Member; Cultural Advisor Co-Director (1988-1990).
1981 -1985 Visiting Lecturer in RTF and CMAS, University of Texas at Austin.
1981, '82, '87 Consultant and international delegate, International Indian Treaty Council.
1982 Participates in Venceremos Brigadeto Cuba.
January 1982 Attends American Indian Movement (AIM) Summit & Leadership Conference, San Francisco, CA.
June 1982 Leads four-person delegation from Austin to June 26 Memorial, Oglala, South Dakota.
1982 -1994 Proprietor, Resistencia Bookstore, Austin, Texas.
1982-1994 Founder, editor, and publisher, Red Salmon Press, Austin, Texas.
July 1984 Attends International Indian Treaty Conference, Sisseton-Wahpheton Reservation, South Dakota. Austin delegation representing the LPDC and Artistas Indigenas.
1985 -1986 St. Louis, Missouri.
1985 -1986 Campaign Coordinator, Leonard Peltier Defense Committee, Eighth Circuit Court of Appeals (St. Louis, Missouri).
1986 -1994 Austin, Texas.
1986 -1989 Youth counselor, South Austin Youth Services.
1987 Delegate and interpreter for International Indian Treaty Council in Geneva, Switzerland,
1987 Delegate for International Indian Treaty Council in Tripoli, Libya, North Africa
1988-1994 Workshop coordinator, Communities in Schools, Austin, TX.
1990 Reads at Inter-American Book Fair, Guadalupe Cultural Arts Center, San Antonio, Texas.
1991 Reads at First Netzahualcoytl Poetry Festival, Mexican Museum of Art, Chicago, Illinois.
1992 Translates for reading by Ernesto Cardenal, Guadalupe Cultural Arts Center, San Antonio, Texas.
1993 Reads at Inter-American book fair at Guadalupe Cultural Arts Center, San Antonio, Texas.
1993-1994 Member, City of Austin Charter Review Committee.
1994 East of the Freeway: Reflections de mi Pueblo. Austin:Red Salmon Press, 1994.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The materials in the collection span from the late 1950s through 1994, and they consist of printed, visual and oral texts. Raul Salinas' writing and political activism reflect a multiplicity of interests and a hybrid of influences. His poetry is formally influenced by the Beat Movement in American literature but derives much of its force from Chicano culture and politics. His literary and political work also evidences his debt to, and influence upon, the American Indian movement and Latin American politics; in this way, Salinas' work typically crosses national traditions and generic forms. The content of the collection is extensive and varied. Series I houses the original manuscripts of Salinas' published and unpublished poetry, essays, and journalism. For example, the original manuscripts of poems which ultimately compose Un Trip Through the Mind Jail y Otras Excursions (Pocho Che, 1980) are herein preserved. Also included are unpublished works such as El Embruje de mi Tio Juan and Tu Mujer; a collection of poetry; and several other manuscripts at varying levels of completion. Recent works represented in the collection are East of the Freeway: Reflections de mi Pueblo and Indio Trails: A Chicano Odyssey through Indian Country. Series II gathers correspondence from the mid-1960s through 1994. These materials trace Salinas' literary and political development through debate and dialogue with such figures as Americo Paredes, Tomas Rivera, Luis Valdez, Jose Montoya, Ricardo Sanchez, Reimundo "Tigre" Perez, Alurista, Juan Felipe Herrera, Fernando Algeria, Francisco Alarcon, Javier Pacheco, Gary Soto, Tomas Ybarra-Frausto, Nina Serrano, Roberto Vargas, Jose Angel Gutierrez, Jose Limon, Joseph Sommers, Stan Steiner, Carlota Cardenas Dwyer, Marcela Trujillo, Lauro Flores, Tom Parson, Juan Rodriguez, Juan Bruce-Novoa, Antonia Castaneda, Leonard Peltier, John Trudell, William Kunstler, and others, including many prisoners whom Salinas met during incarceration. Salinas' prison experiences, which date from 1957 through 1972, contributed significantly to his development as artist, activist, and scholar. Among other documents, Series III includes landmark litigation initiated by various prisoner-rights groups, of which Salinas was an active member. Salinas' activities with the American Indian Movement (A.I.M.) and the International Indian Treaty Council, for which he served as a delegate, spokesperson, and translator, are documented in Series X. This portion of the Collection includes official reports and position papers, many of which he co-authored, as well as internal correspondence related to such cases as Wounded Knee and the Pine Ridge incident, which ultimately involved Leonard Peltier. The Collection contains Salinas' assortment of rare literary and political texts, journals, magazines, and newspapers in Series VIII. Among these are Fuego de Aztlan (1976); Corazon de Aztlan (1971), La Voz de Aztlan (Vol. 1, Nos. 1-2), Aztlan de Leavenworth (1970-71); New Era (1970-71); La Raza (Vol. 1, Nos. 1-12), El Travieso (1969); Miquiztli (de Estanfort) (1972-1977); Canto al Pueblo (1978); El Pocho Che (all editions); Rasca Tripas (1970); Regeneracion (1970); Magazin (Vol. 1, Nos. 1-9); Sin Fronteras (all editions); Tejidos (all editions); and Con Safos (all editions) Additionally, Salinas has preserved original copies of all the journals, magazines, and anthologies where his work first appeared. The Collection houses various personal documents, photographs, videos, recordings, and an assortment of miscellaneous items such as fliers, posters, buttons, and decals (for instance, those of Floricanto, Canto al Pueblo, and other festivals). Series V contains the only still photos of performers at the First Annual Floricanto Festival held at the University of Southern California Campus in 1973, as well as numerous photos from the Huntsville, Leavenworth, and Marion prisons.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series 1. Manuscripts
  - Autobiografik All Notes n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Calle 25 Poems [fragments] n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - East of the Freeway. AMS, fragments. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - East of the Freeway. TMs. [1 of 2] n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - East of the Freeway. TMs. [2 of 2] n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Historia de una Lucha: Story of a Struggle. TMs. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Indio Trails. AMs. [1 of 2] n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Indio Trails. AMs. [2 of 2] n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Jazz Years [for Poems in Progress] n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Mural Destruction Painful Loss for Chicanos," EL AVISO. TMs. 1982 June/ July (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Music for the Masses. TMs. c. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Poemas en Espa-ol. AMs, Fragments. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Portrait of an Artist. 3TMs, n.d. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Prison Journals. AMs, TMs, misc. fragments. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Prison Tattoos n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Prison and the Press (an overview). TMs. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Radio Transcripts n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Transcibed poems & quotations. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Un Trip Through the Mind Jail y Otras Excursions. AMs fragments. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Un Trip Through the Mind Jail y Otras Excursions. Unedited TMs. [1 of 5] n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Un Trip Through the Mind Jail y Otras Excursions. Unedited TMs. [2 of 5] n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Un Trip Through the Mind Jail y Otras Excursions. Unedited TMs. [3 of 5] n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Un Trip Through the Mind Jail y Otras Excursions. Unedited TMs. [4 of 5] n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Un Trip Through the Mind Jail y Otras Excursions. Unedited TMs. [5 of 5] n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Un Trip Through the Mind Jail y Otras Excursions. Final TMs. [1 of 2] 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Un Trip Through the Mind Jail y Otras Excursions. Final TMs. [2 of 2] 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Tu Mujer. TMs. n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tu Mujer. Galleys. n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified Manuscripts. n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Misc. Prison Notes & Writings. [1 of 2] n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Misc. Prison Notes & Writings. [2 of 2] n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series 2. Correspondence
  - Subseries A. Chronological
    - 1970 & Before (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - 1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Subseries B. Alphabetical
    - Alarc-n, Francisco n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Alegria, Fernando. [University of Washington] 1974 Feb. 27 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Alejandro, Ann n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Alurista. [U.T. C.M.A.S.] 1975 May 20 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Antonio, José n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Armas, Jose 1976 Apr. 15 -1976 Jul. 23 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Aztlán de Leavenworth. 1971 Oct. 26 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Barrientos, Gonzalo. [Texas congressman] 1986 Feb. 20 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Binder, Wolfgang 1980 Apr. 22 -1983 Jul. 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Bonald, José Manuel Caballero n.d. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Brown, Faye n.d. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bruce-Novoa, Juan. [Yale University] 1975 Oct. 4 -1981 Nov. 13 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Burciaga, José Antonio 1972 Jan. 25 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Calapooya Collage n.d. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Cambon, Glauco (Italy) 1971 Oct. 28 -1971 Jun. 27 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Canto Al Pueblo 1981 Mar. 2 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Cardenas, Antonio. [University of Washington] 1973 May 3 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Cárdenas, Teresa 1973 Apr. 23 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Casta-eda, Antonia 1971 Oct. 12 -1974 Jan. 3 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Centro de Estudios Sobre America n.d. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Chac-n, Ernesto 1978 Oct. 27 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - ChidrenÕs Letters n.d. (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Cisneros, Sandra 1984 Nov. -1985 Apr. (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Clark, Donald. 1971 Apr. 12 -Jun. 28 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Cortez, Carlos 1992 Dec. 28 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - DeLeon, Nephtal' 1976 -1977 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Delgado, Abelardo 1982 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Doane, Mary. [Houghton- Mifflin] 1975 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Dwyer, C. Cardenas (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Egar, Ernestina N. 1978 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Empringham, Toni. [El Camino College] 1980 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Estrella, Ruben. [Prison compa] 1972 -1 974 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Familia n.d. (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Flores, Lauro 1983 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Franklin, Bruce 1973 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Fulton, Len 1972 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Gabino, Keme 1982 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Galeria n.d. (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Gerardo, Victor n.d. (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Gordon, Jaimy 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Graham, Wes. [IN Magazine] 1972 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Guadalupe Cultural Arts Center n.d. (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Guerra, Blanca Estela n.d. (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Gutierrez, José A. [Raza Unida] 1972-1977 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Hall, Ellen 1971 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Harth, Dorothy E. [Onondaga Community College] 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Hernandez, Paul 1982-1988 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Hoehne, Charles N. 1972 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Horoscope 1971 Mar. 21 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Hunter College 1984 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Kirk, Janice n.d. (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Lambert, Liz n.d. (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Lara-Braud, Jorge 1970 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - L'mon, José. [UT CMAS] 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Madrid-Barela, Arturo. [U. of Minnesota] 1974 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Maestas, Roberto. El Centro 1990 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Magoo n.d. (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - MALDEF 1972 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Mares, Alberto 1972 -1975 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Martinez, Eliud 1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Martinez, Elizabeth n.d. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - M.A.R.A. [Aztlan de Leavenworth] 1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - May 19th - Sara Baraldini n.d. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - McPherson, Bruce n.d. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Mendoza, Armando n.d. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Miers, Rudy. [Comile Floricanto] n.d. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Miranda, Rafael - P.R. Nationalist 1971-1977 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Montalvo, Jose 1982 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Montoya, Jose 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Montoya, Malaquias n.d. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Moore, Joan. [UC Riverside] 1971 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Moraga, Cherr'e n.d. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Murgu'a, Alejandra n.d. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Native American: Survival of American Indian Association n.d. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - National/ International Postcards n.d. (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - New Era Magazine 1971 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Ortego, Philip 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Ortiz, Roxanne Dunbar n.d. (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Pacheco, Mary Ann.[University of Southern California] 1974 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Pachero, Javier 1976 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Paredes, Américo. [UT CMAS] 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Parra, Ricardo 1971 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Parson, Tom 1977 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Peace & Justice Coalition n.d. (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Peltier, Leonard 1978-1985 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Peltier Defence Committee 1981-1984 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Perez, Reimundo "Tigre" 1973-1982 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Plamondon, Pun & Genie 1972 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Ressler, Allen 1972 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Rivera, Tomás. [U.T.S.A.] 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Rodriguez, Andres n.d. (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Rodriguez, Juan. [U.C. Berkeley] 1978 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Rodriguez, Pedro 1980 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Rothwell, Geoff. [Evergreen State College] 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Rudolph, Karen n.d. (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Ruiz, Francisco. [Penn Valley College] 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Sald'var, Ramon. [U.T. CMAS] 1985 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - S.F. Mime Troupe 1968-1981 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Salinas, Judy n.d. (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Sanchez, Ricardo. [El Paso Community Colleg] 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Sanchez, Rosaura. [U.C. San Diego] 1989 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Serrano, Nina. n.d. (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Smith, Phil n.d. (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Sommers, Joseph 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Sosa, Arturo n.d. (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Soto, Gary 1978 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Steiner, Stan 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Taylor, "Chuck" n.d. (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Taylor, Pat Ellis ["Little Dog"] n.d. (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Toltecas en Aztlan n.d. (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Trevi-o, Albert D. n.d. (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Trujillo, Marcela. [University of Minnesota] 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - University Central America Peace Initiative n.d. (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Valdez, Lu's 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Vance, William L. n.d. (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Vargas, Beto n.d. (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Venceremos Brigade n.d. (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Villanueva, Tino 1973-1981 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Yarbro-Bejarano, Yvonne 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Ybarra-Frausto, Tomás n.d. (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Zamora, Bernice 1977 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Unidentified Correspondence n.d. (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Misc. Notes n.d. (Box 5, Folder 65)
- Series 3: Legal and Penal Activism
  - Probation card (juvenile) n. d. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Marion n. d. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Legal Documents [Juvenile Court of Travis County, Texas] 1947 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Legal Documents [Juvenile Court of Travis County, Texas] 1948 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Legal Documents[LONG, Bob; District Attorney, County of Travis, Texas) 1951 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Legal Document [County of Travis, Texas] 1953 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Legal Documents [California Adult Authority] 1958 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Legal Documents [California Adult Authority] 1959 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Legal Documents [Texas Department of Corrections] 1961 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Legal Documents [Texas Department of Corrections] 1962 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Legal Documents [Texas Department of Corrections] 1964 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Legal Documents 1965 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Legal Documents [Texas Board of Pardons and Paroles] 1966 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Legal Documents [US Penitentiary, Leavenworth] 1967 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clippings on SalinasÕ drug arrests 1967 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Legal Documents [newspaper clippings] 1968 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Legal Documents 1969 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - US Court of Appeals, No 28670 1970 Apr. 17 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Legal Documents [PICKETT, George W., US Penitentiary, Marion IL.] 1971 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Legal Documents [1 of 2] 1972 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Legal Documents [2 of 2] 1972 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Legal Documents 1973 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Legal Documents 1974 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Legal Documents 1975 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Political Prisoners 1975 (Box 6, Folder 25)